<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="tei_bare.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="MSH">
    <teiHeader xml:id="teiHeader_d1e4">
        <fileDesc xml:id="fileDesc_d1e6">
            <titleStmt xml:id="titleStmt_d1e8">
                <title xml:id="title_d1e10">منتخب صوان الحكمة</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt xml:id="publicationStmt_d1e14">
                <p xml:id="p_d1e16">Sharing Ancient Wisdoms</p>
                <p xml:id="p_d1e19">http://www.ancientwisdoms.ac.uk</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc xml:id="sourceDesc_d1e23">
                <list xml:id="list_d1e25">
                    <label xml:id="label_d1e27">country</label>
                    <item xml:id="item_d1e30">Austria</item>
                    <label xml:id="label_d1e33">settlement</label>
                    <item xml:id="item_d1e36">Vienna</item>
                    <label xml:id="label_d1e39">repository</label>
                    <item xml:id="item_d1e43">Fachbereichsbibliothek Afrikawissenschaften und Orientalistik</item>
                    <label xml:id="label_d1e46">idno</label>
                    <item xml:id="item_d1e49">ArNa5o</item>
                </list>
            </sourceDesc>
            <sourceDesc xml:id="sourceDesc_d1e54">
                <p xml:id="p_d1e56">Incomplete version of Abū Sulaimān as-Sijistānīs collection of Greek wisdoms</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:id="text_d1e62">
        <body xml:id="body_d1e64">
            <div xml:id="div_d1e66">
                <head xml:id="head_d1e68">Thales of Miletus </head>
                <div xml:id="Thales_tr">
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_n1"> He was the first who started philosophy, and due to him a
                        group of the Greeks was called philosophers. He [caused] a significant
                        revolution for philosophy. This man practiced philosophy in Egypt and he
                        came to Miletus. He was a sage. Only a few of his sayings still exist due to
                        the progression and the passing of an extended period of time. This is what
                        he said: </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_s1"> The truth is not praiseworthy, but rather it is praised
                        because it is more elevated and higher than the praise(worthy), and yet we
                        praise the things which, when performed, can tend either to the good or the
                        bad. </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_n2"> He said: </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_s2"> The most dishonourable things are: An oath sworn in truth,
                        but nevertheless causing disgrace, an insult of an incapable person, anger
                        as a result of narrow mindedness, and regret about a past failure. </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_n3"> He said: </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_s3"> Whoever performs an action in secret, yet is embarrassed
                        by it in public, is a worthless person. </p>
                    <p xml:id="Tha_tr_n4"> He said: </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_s4"> He who does not feel that there is a rational soul inside
                        him, but just feels that he is wearing a mortal body, is an animal and
                        necessarily concerned by what animals do, and he who feels that there is an
                        immortal rational soul inside him must not be concerned by what animals do,
                        but is obliged to imitate the acts of God, the sublime. </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_n5"> He was asked: </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_s5"> Why are those who do something bad punished for their
                        deeds, whereas those who (only) intend to do something bad are not
                        (punished)? </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_n6"> And he said: </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_s6"> Intended on the part of man is not that he does not think,
                        but that he does not do the bad thing he is thinking of. </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_n7"> He was asked: </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_s7"> Which living creature does not become satisfied? </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_n8"> And he said: </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_s8"> The human being that profits. </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_n9"> He said: </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_s9"> In great distress is he to whom the severity of the
                        sincere advisor appears to be less important than the softness of the
                        flattering secret enemy. </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_n10"> And he said: </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_s10"> If you exhort a sinner, treat him gently so that he does
                        not manifest open (hostility). </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_n11"> He said: </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_s11"> Be more afraid of someone who perfidiously conceals (the
                        truth) from you than of someone who openly reveals (it), because the
                        treatment of apparent diseases is easier than the treatment of what has
                        become invisible and hidden. </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_n12"> He said: </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_s12"> Someone who gives you something bitter to drink so that
                        you recover is more sympathetic than someone who pours something sweet down
                        your throat so that you become ill, and someone who scares you so that you
                        escape to safety is more honest with you than someone who stays friendly
                        until you (suddenly) find yourself in danger. </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_n13"> It was said to him: </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_s13"> Remove/Dispel this grief from your heart! </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_n14"> And he said: </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_s14"> It did not enter with my permission. </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_n15"> He was asked about his state (of health), after he had
                        become senile, and he said: </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_s15"> It is so: I am dying slowly. </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_n16"> He said: </p>
                    <p xml:id="Th_tr_s16"> The (true) word that is irrefutable is the Creator and
                        not something created. He creates what is created, and he has no form in
                        himself, for there was only him before creation. If only he exists, it is
                        not said at a certain moment that such and such (exists) except him and how
                        he is, through what he is and why he is, is (all) inside him. Creation is to
                        make something existent from something that does not exist. If something is
                        made existent (at all), then making it existent is never like the Maker (of
                        this existent), but like what is outside him. There is no doubt that there
                        is definitely no form for what is made existent, and (what is made existent)
                        does not give existence. And if it is him who makes the things existent,
                        then making existent is not from something preexistent. The non-existent
                        thing is what is made existent and not what gives existence. If this is the
                        case, then he who makes the things existent does not need to have the form
                        of something because of his existence, or else, if there is a (single) form
                        with him, it would be necessary that he was connected with the form[s] that
                        is with him. For the forms that would be with him would be eternally and
                        separately existing. There is no doubt that he who is connected with those
                        forms would be the first creation if the forms reached infinity. So it
                        cannot be that there are forms with him, otherwise he would not be the
                        creator. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>